Good morning. Today's דף ד. daf daled. We pick up at the
bottom of ג עמוד ב. gimmel amud beis. We have learned, we
have a discussion that the morning שמע Shma goes till the end
according to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of the first אשמורה, ashmora, which
could be three hours or four hours. We believe according to רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer it's four hours, so it's till about 10 p.m.
And we got into a whole discussion about אשמורה ashmora and various
verses, various contexts and now we're hearing that דוד המלך Dovid Hamelech
would get up at midnight to praise God.
And the גמרא's Gemara now continuing with that and he did it
because of this west, of this northern wind which would blow through
his harp and wake him up. So now we pick up at
the bottom of ג עמוד ב. gimmel amud beis.
Let's go from the line ונושבת בו. venoshevas bo. It is seven
lines from the bottom beginning of a line. So this northern wind
would come ונושבת בו, venoshevas bo, blow in the harp ומנגן מאליו
umnagei me'eilav and the harp would play by itself at midnight, מיד
היה עומד ועוסק בתורה miyad hayah omeid ve'osek batorah and he would
rise up and learn תורה, Torah, which is interesting because a minute
ago we had said in the verse it said that he gets
up at חצות להודות לך chatzos lehodos lach to praise God and
maybe the learning of תורה's Torah prior, but here anyway it's framing
it that he gets up at חצות chatzos to learn תורה. Torah.
עד שעלה עמוד השחר ad she'alah amud hashachar until the morning star
comes up, until the daybreak an hour or so before sunrise. כיון
שעלה עמוד השחר keivan she'alah amud hashachar the morning star comes up,
נכנסו חכמי ישראל אצלו, nichnasu chachmei Yisrael etzlo, the Jewish, the sages
of ישראל Yisrael come to him. These are
his representatives from the country, his sages, the people to discuss the
policy for the country. אמרו לו amru lo they said to him,
אדונינו המלך, adoneinu hamelech, our master king, עמך ישראל צריכין פרנסה. amcha
Yisrael tzrichin parnassah. The nation of ישראל Israel needs to make a
פרנסה, parnassah, they need to make money, things aren't going so well
financially. אמר להם amar lahem he said to them, לכו והתפרנסו זה
מזה, lechu ve'isparnasu zeh mizeh, go do business with each other. So
one person sells to the other person, what's the big deal, so
go do business with one another. אמרו לו amru lo they said
to him, אין הקומץ משביע את הארי. ein hakometz masbia es ha'ari.
The tiny little hand-breath of food does not satisfy the lion. Our
needs are much greater, again the lion is interesting echoing what we
learned yesterday about God roaring out like a lion. Anyway, what we
can provide for one another is very small and our needs are
very great, that won't do it. ואין הבור מתמלא מחולייתו. v'ein habor
mismalei meichulyasa. Now this is an interesting phrase, some read it to
mean a pit cannot be filled from the dirt that it was
hollowed out. Of course that's not true because you hollow out a
pit, normally the dirt is less well packed and then you pour
it back in, actually it more than fills the dirt. So there's
an interesting couple of explanations. רש"י Rashi says what it means is
you already have a pit, if you pull out like a little
clump of earth from within the pit and throw it back in,
you're not going to fill the pit. And actually that's not a
bad metaphor. Here we are and we've got a lot of needs,
we're in the red. What are you telling us to do? Take
from some part of us and put it into try to fill
our needs, but you're anyway taking away from one place and you're
not going to fill a big hole. You've got a big hole
here. Where are you going to get the dirt from within a
hole to fill the hole? Like try to fill the hole from
within the hole, you're not going to fill it. So תוספות Tosafos
has a couple of other explanations, they all sort of boil down
to the same thing. One is רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam that says
well he wants to say well there's a water running underneath the
well, you still can't fill up the well from the water from
the stream that's at the bottom of the well. So the rich
people are the stream but still it's not enough to fill the
hole, it's not enough to fill the well.
And the ר"י Ri explained more or less the same type of
a thing, that you try to dig here and move it over
here, you're just going to create a hole where you dug it
from. Okay, so you can't tell us to do business with ourselves,
there's too great of a need and you're just moving around, you're
robbing from Peter to pay Paul and you're not going to actually,
we need to make money outside of what we ourselves have. We
ourselves don't have enough money. So that's what they said to him.
By the way, notice though the respectful way in which they answer.
They don't say that's wrong, that won't work. They answer by like
a metaphor.
The hand-breath doesn't satisfy the lion. So obviously they don't tell the
king that he's wrong. So that's what he said. So what does
he say back? אמר להם amar lahem he said back to them,
לכו ופשטו ידיכם בגדוד. lechu upshitu yedeichem begedud. Okay, so
you
don't, you can't make enough פרנסה, parnassah, can't make enough money from
doing business with yourselves? Go out to war. Which is a pretty
shocking type of response. Actually sometimes it works. Second World
War really did a lot for the economy of the United States.
But of course we've been in a lot of wars recently in
the United States, in ישראל Israel or whatever, that can besides tremendous
loss of life and often tremendous drag on the economy. And it's
also a pretty interesting response that there's that just like oh what
do you have to do to make money, you go to war.
Well what about the other, what about the loss of life that
we're dealing with on our side and on the other side? So
maybe it somehow means a war that anyway he would have been
fighting, but it's I think it raises certain questions.
Is there any הלכתי halachic significance to that
to saying go to war?
People when Jews are in poverty. impoverished? Yeah, you can just attack?
Well, you know, obviously for like two thousand years from the time
the גמרא Gemara was written, it was a moot point roughly, but
the question, you know, not now, it's not now, right. So that's
why I think that that raises serious questions that it's just that
sort of casual type of a response. Have people quoted this, you
know, in the הלכה? Halacha? No, this is not quoted in הלכה.
Halacha. No. But what is we are going to see is is
that the, you know, the גמרא Gemara talks about and the רמב״ם
Rambam further categorizes two categories of war, like מלחמת מצוה Milchemet Mitzvah
and מלחמת רשות. Milchemet Reshut. And מלחמת רשות, Milchemet Reshut, you know,
what constitutes רשות, Reshut, you don't just, you know, we'll see in
a minute that there's actually some type of a process that you
need to get God's blessing in it, but basically רשות Reshut is,
you know, just a desire for territorial expansion.
Like here? Like here, it's desire to like, you know, improve the
economy. Like you do to other people. Right, you get other people,
you get their wealth. Right, exactly. Exactly. So that is the category
of of מלחמת רשות, Milchemet Reshut, meaning the category of conquering the
land of Israel, the war against the שבעה עממים Shiva Amamim or
destroying עמלק, Amalek, you know, things that raise questions on their own,
but those clearly in are those are מלחמת מצוה Milchemet Mitzvah Ye.
Also, you know, what the רמב״ם Rambam makes very clear is מלחמת
מצוה Milchemet Mitzvah includes wars of defense or self-defense when you're being
attacked and so on. But מלחמת רשות Milchemet Reshut is basically done
for territorial expansion. But that's not, you know, based on this גמרא,
Gemara, but you're right, it's not significantly different. I mean, you know,
what territorial expansion? You want more, you know, maybe you want more
because you need more, maybe you want more because you're just never
satisfied with what you have. But it's a that's a war of
מלחמת רשות. Milchemet Reshut.
Yeah, that is a הלכה Halacha category. And you're right, I mean,
that does raise questions about, you know, legitimizing what legitimizes war. So
let's see where the גמרא Gemara goes with this.
So
מיד, Miyad, יועצין באחיתופל, yoatzin b'Achitofel, they get advice from אחיתופל, Achitofel,
who is the advisor. ונמלכין בסנהדרין, V'nimlachin b'Sanhedrin, then they get permission.
Meaning the difference between יועצין yoatzin and נמלכין nimlachin is נמלכין nimlachin
is ask permission. They ask permission from the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. ושואלין באורים
ותומים, V'shoalin b'Urim v'Tumim, and they also ask from the אורים ותומים,
Urim v'Tumim, which is the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol wears אורים ותומים,
Urim v'Tumim, and that, you know, was understood you ask the כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol in these types of. We actually have one of
the early uses of the אורים ותומים Urim v'Tumim in תנ״ך Tanach
was when they were going out to war and it would go
up, יהודה יעלה, Yehuda yaaleh, you know, they got the answer you
go up, and who goes up first, and so on, how you
fight the war. So they asked the אורים ותומים, Urim v'Tumim, they
get God's permission. And there, and then they go to war. אמר
רב יוסף מאי קרא, Amar Rav Yosef mai kra, what's the פסוק?
pasuk? ואחרי אחיתופל, V'acharei Achitofel, בניהו בן יהוידע Benayahu ben Yehoyada came
בניהו בן יהוידע, Benayahu ben Yehoyada, ואביתר, v'Evyatar, and then ואביתר v'Evyatar
ושר צבא למלך יואב, v'sar tzava lamelech Yoav, and they and then
the and then the general of the king which was יואב. Yoav.
And now we're going to identify all the players. אחיתופל זה יועץ,
Achitofel zeh yoetz, אחיתופל Achitofel was the advisor. וכן הוא אומר, V'chen
hu omer, ועצת אחיתופל אשר יעץ בימים ההם כאשר ישאל בדבר האלקים.
va'atzat Achitofel asher yaatz bayamim hahem ka'asher yishal bidvar Ha'elokim. The advice
from אחיתופל Achitofel that people would ask in those days, it would
be such great advice it would be like asking the word of
God. So you ask, you get, you get the input of your
advisors, whether it's good policy, any good king would do that. And
then בניהו בן יהוידע, Benayahu ben Yehoyada, then you get the סנהדרין's,
Sanhedrin okay, imprimatur. Top of דף טז עמוד א, daf tet-zayin amud
aleph, זה סנהדרין. zeh Sanhedrin. We don't know yet how we know
that. ואביתר אלו אורים ותומים, V'Evyatar elu Urim v'Tumim, and ואביתר v'Evyatar
who was the כהן, Kohen, that's אורים ותומים. Urim v'Tumim. וכן הוא
אומר, V'chen hu omer, the פסוק pasuk says, ובניהו בן יהוידע על
הכרתי ועל הפלתי. u'Vnayahu ben Yehoyada al ha-Kreiti v'al ha-Pleiti. So I'll
tell you how רש״י Rashi reads it and how תוספות Tosafot reads
it. בניהו בן יהוידע Benayahu ben Yehoyada came על al prior to
the כרתי ופלתי, Kreiti u'Pleiti, which is the אורים ותומים. Urim v'Tumim.
ולמה נקרא שמם כרתי ופלתי? V'lama nikra shemam Kreiti u'Pleiti?
Why are they called the כרתי ופלתי, Kreiti u'Pleiti, the אורים ותומים?
Urim v'Tumim? כרתי שכורתים דבריהם, Kreiti shekortim divreihem, the כרתי Kreiti that
their words are sort of cut, are you know, are are given
out in very definitive form. ופלתי שמופלאים בדבריהם, U'Pleiti shemuflaim b'divreihem, their
words are astounding. So the words that come out, you know, according
to חז״ל, Chazal, the way the אורים ותומים Urim v'Tumim would work
is that on the breastplate of אהרן, Aharon, the names of all
the tribes would be inscribed, and it would have the letters of
the אלף בית, aleph-beit, there were also some other like letters on
top. And then when you asked, you know, a question, the letters
would somehow rearrange themselves and you would get an answer, and that
would be God's answer. So that's the word it was astounding, and
it was explicit, and that was the כרתי ופלתי. Kreiti u'Pleiti. ואחר
כך, V'achar kach, and then the end of the פסוק pasuk is
שר צבא למלך יואב, sar tzava lamelech Yoav, then you go to
war, then you go to the general. Now תוספות Tosafot says
that no, we know
אביתר Evyatar was the אורים ותומים. Urim v'Tumim. He was basically the
only כהן Kohen left alive after שאול Shaul had wiped out נוב
עיר הכהנים. Nov ir ha-Kohanim. So there's no question that אביתר Evyatar
was the אורים ותומים, Urim v'Tumim, you don't need a פסוק pasuk
for that. That's who he represents. What we need a פסוק pasuk
is how you know בניהו בן יהוידע Benayahu ben Yehoyada was the
head of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. That's not clear in the פסוק pasuk
at all. רש״י Rashi says, well, we just know it sort of
like we assume it, it's really not in the פסוק, pasuk, but
it seems like we're trying to prove these things. So תוספות Tosafot
says, ובניהו בן יהוידע על הכרתי ועל הפלתי, u'Vnayahu ben Yehoyada al
ha-Kreiti v'al ha-Pleiti, didn't mean he preceded the כרתי ופלתי, Kreiti u'Pleiti,
means he was over, he was he was the head of the
כרתי ופלתי, Kreiti u'Pleiti, and the כרתי ופלתי Kreiti u'Pleiti is the
סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. And that also explains the plural language
here, שכרתים דבריהם שמופלאים בדבריהם. shekortim divreihem shemuflaim b'divreihem. That this פסוק
pasuk *pasuk* is בניה בן יהוידע *Benaiah ben Yehoyada*, the
earlier פסוק Pasuk. *pasuk*, of although the way it's quoted in the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is בניהו בן יהוידע *Benaiahu ben Yehoyada*, the way
it actually is in דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim, *Divrei HaYamim* is יהוידע
בן בניהו *Yehoyada ben Benaiahu*. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* sort of
is like equating the two. But anyway, here you go about this
process of asking permission. So it's an interesting question like we sort
of understand why any king wants some advice. We understand that at
the beginning. We understand you finally give over the orders to the
general at the end. We understand getting God's okay, right? It's going
out to war and actually if you look in תנ״ך *Tanakh*, one
of the first uses of, you know, the אורים ותומים *Urim ve-Tumim*
was asking like should we be going to war? Is it the
right thing? A, will we be successful? B, is it the right
thing to be doing? Sort of getting, you know, God's okay. What
is the role of the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*? So if you look, there's
an interesting רש״י Rashi, *Rashi* here, about five lines from the bottom
on ג׳ עמוד ב׳ *Gimel amud bet*. רש״י Rashi *Rashi* says ונמלכין
בסנהדרין *v'nimlakhin be-Sanhedrin*. He says נוטלין מהם רשות כדי שיתפללו עליהם *notlin
mehem reshut kedei she-yitpalelu aleihem*. Right?
Very strange. They should pray on their behalf, and it's not strange
that you want the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* and the people to pray on
your behalf, but it's very strange that that's why they are, why
you ask permission from them. I mean you assume once you've decided
you're going to war, then you ask the people to pray for
you. And you would have thought that getting permission from the סנהדרין
*Sanhedrin* was that the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* represent although not exactly an elected
body, but they're understood many times to represent the people. Right? Like
when there's, you do the ritual of the עגלה ערופה *eglah arufah*,
the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* goes out and lays their hand on the עגלה
ערופה *eglah arufah*. Why the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin*? Because they represent the people.
So you would think you want the people's implicit imprimatur and God's
explicit imprimatur, so you go to the סנהדרין *Sanhedrin* and you go
to the אורים ותומים *Urim ve-Tumim*. So I find this רש״י *Rashi*,
that shifts it to you that they'll pray for you. You also
want them to pray for you, but again, I find that strange
that that's why they're being asked, you know, that you assume would
be sort of after the fact. But maybe you want to know
you have the people behind you praying for you as well, but
it still seems that the permission idea is something different than that.
Yes.
Other, the אורים ותומים *Urim ve-Tumim* are often compared to oracular devices,
but in the ancient world, most oracles from the non-Jews would speak
very cryptically.
Ah, interesting. So maybe that's the emphasis, that it's very explicit and
very clear. Right.
That's interesting. Of course, sometimes they, you know, things get mixed up
there as well, like I'll just tell you a cute thing, I
think it's the הגר״א *ha-Gra* says or whatever, that when, that when
חנה *Hannah*, you know, was,
was, you know, was praying for a
child, right, and eventually she's going to have שמואל Shmuel, *Shmuel*, so
it says ויחשבה עלי לשכורה *v'yakhsheveha Eli le-shikhorah*. Right? So עלי *Eli*
thought that she was drunk. And she said, no, I'm praying because
I'm so, you know, distraught and so on. So the גאון מווילנא
*Gaon mi-Vilna* says I don't understand, like he had the אורים ותומים
*Urim ve-Tumim*, how could he get it wrong? So he says well,
because
he saw letters, ש-כ-ר-ה *Shin-Kaf-Resh-Heh*. So he's rearranged, he rearranged it, he
thought it meant שכורה *shikhorah*, she's drunk, but really it was saying
כשרה *kesherah*, that she's like שרה *Sarah* because she's infertile. Anyway, so
that's a cute little ווארט *vort*, but the point, your point about
how explicit it always was, or how often open to misinterpretation, that's
a good question, you know, when you deal with these as you
said, these sort of divine messages. Yes.
It seems from the next רש״י *Rashi*, ושואלין באורים ותומים אם יצליחו
*ve-sho'alin be-Urim ve-Tumim im yatzlikhu*, that it's not a matter of permission.
You're right. The next רש״י *Rashi*, thank you for pointing that out.
The next רש״י *Rashi* makes the same point, that somehow, you're right,
I meant to, my point meant to mention that. That even though
רש״י *Rashi* says by the, by ונמלכין בסנהדרין *v'nimlakhin be-Sanhedrin*, נוטלין רשות
*notlin reshut*, and these words do seem to indicate that you are
asking for permission, רש״י *Rashi* does seem to frame it as you
know what you're going to do, right, and you just want people's
blessings. But you're plan, you're doing it anyway, you're not asking for
permission. Absolutely right. Point ever since. And you want to make sure
you're going to win, but you don't necessarily actually really need permission.
So thank you, yeah, I find that, that's strange. I would not
have thought that's what was going on. Okay, so let's continue now
in the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, continuing here on דף ג׳ עמוד ב׳
*daf gimel amud bet*. ואחר כך שר צבא המלך *v'akhar kakh sar
tzeva ha-melekh*, then you give it over to the general. אמר Amar
רב יצחק בר אדא ואמרי לה אמר Amar, רב יצחק בריה דרב
אידי *amar Rav Yitzchak bar Adda v'amrei lah amar Rav Yitzchak bereih
de-Rav Idi*, מאי קרא mai kra? *mai kra*, where's the פסוק Pasuk
*pasuk* that you see that דוד המלך David HaMelech. *David HaMelekh* would
get up early? I mean we quoted a פסוק Pasuk? *pasuk* earlier
that he'd get up at חצות chatzos *Chatzot*, but here we're talking
that he's not getting up at חצות chatzos *Chatzot* to learn, but
that he's also getting involved in the business of kings, you know,
in the running of the country very early, even before sunrise. Where
do you see this from? עורה כבודי עורה הנבל וכנור אעירה שחר
*urah kevodi urah ha-nevel ve-khinnor a'irah shachar*. Bestir my honor, meaning bestir
myself, bestir the נבל *nevel* and the כנור *kinnor*, so the כנור
*kinnor* is the harp. I got the musical instruments wrong yesterday. What's
a נבל *nevel*? Anybody know? Also some type of a, of a
string instrument? Or is this time, anybody know? I always get these,
the instruments wrong. What, a psalter?
Psaltery and harp?
Psalter. I don't know what that means.
Something for playing psalms? Right.
All right. Anyway, so let's... these be עורה, so also having to
do of course with presumably the harp. And then אעירה השחר, A'irah
Hashachar, which means I will wake up the morning. The morning won't
wake me up, I will wake up the morning. I'll be up
before the morning is up. Okay, רש"י Rashi says it very nicely:
שאר מלכים השחר מעוררן, She'ar melachim hashachar me'oran,
other kings need the morning to wake them up, ואני מעורר השחר,
va'ani me'orer hashachar, I get up so early I wake up the
morning. רבי זירא אמר, Rabbi Zeira amar, so now anyway that was
by the way, if you remember, a little bit of a digression
from how did דוד Dovid not know when how did דוד Dovid
know when it was חצות chatzos if משה Moshe didn't. So it
said oh he had this alarm clock, the harp played. רבי זירא
אמר משה לעולם הוי ידע. Rabbi Zeira amar Moshe le'olam havay yada.
You know what, דוד Dovid did משה, Moshe, the question was not
just how did דוד Dovid know but how did דוד Dovid know
and משה Moshe not know? משה Moshe said כחצות. kechatzos. משה Moshe
also knew when exactly midnight was. ודוד נמי הוי ידע, Vedovid nami
havay yada, and דוד Dovid also knew, you didn't need a harp,
somehow they were so wise that they could know through not telling
us exactly how exactly when midnight was without clocks. וכיון דדוד הוי
ידע כינור למה לי, Vekivan deDovid havay yada kinor lamay ley, so
if that's true that דוד Dovid did know what about this harp?
I mean that you know we learned from verses before that we
understand that this harp is what woke up דוד. Dovid. So the
גמרא Gemara says לאתרויי משינתיה, Le'itruy mishinasei, to wake him up. It
was an alarm clock! Not that he needed to know exactly when
חצות chatzos was, he could have figured that out himself, but he
needed to get some sleep so he needed the harp to wake
him up. Alright. וכיון דמשה הוי ידע, Vekivan deMoshe havay yada, if
משה Moshe knew when חצות chatzos? was, למה לי למימר כחצות? lamay
ley lemeimar kechatzos? Why did he say
approximately חצות chatzos, God will come out? Why didn't he say exactly
at חצות? chatzos. משה קסבר, Moshe kasavar, משה Moshe says I know
that it was exactly חצות, chatzos שמא יטעו
אצטגניני פרעה, shema yitu itagninei Paroh, maybe the astrologers of פרעה Paroh
will make a mistake. Why mention astrologers? Obviously because at night how
do you tell time? By looking at the stars. So that's how
you try to approximate time. So maybe they will make a mistake,
ויאמרו משה בדאי הוא, veyomru Moshe baday hu, and they'll say משה's
Moshe a liar. Look, he said it was going to come at
midnight and it didn't, it came a little bit before, it came
a little bit after. We don't have to pay any attention to
it. It obviously is all fake anyway because he was wrong, it
wasn't at exactly at חצות. chatzos דאמר מר, de'amar mar, because we
and this follows the teaching that we're taught, למד לשונך לומר איני
יודע, lameid leshonecha lomar eini yodeia, you should always teach yourself to
say I don't know, שמא תתבדה ותאחז, shema tispadei vesochazei, maybe you
will be like make it up and be found wrong and you
will be caught in your lie or in your imprecision, in your
mistake. And obviously it's a little bit different because what the מסכת
דרך ארץ, maseches Derech Eretz, this is a line from מסכת דרך
ארץ maseches Derech Eretz which is teaching sort of like good מוסר
mussar and good ways of you know acting in this world, is
saying is if you don't know, there's very often the human inclination
is to fudge it a little bit. Right? To answer even though
you're not exactly sure. And it says you know that's not so
smart because besides the fact it's not proper to lie but you'll
get caught out, you know? And you'll say things and they won't
be accurate and people will see that they can't trust what you're
saying. But that's when you actually don't know. Here it even a
little goes beyond that. משה Moshe did know. But even so he
was so much concerned that people shouldn't think that he had made
a mistake that he would rather be imprecise and say I don't
exactly know rather than even say what is correct and have it
lead to people thinking that he didn't know what he was talking
about and that he was making a mistake. So presumably it's a
קל וחומר kal vachomer how much more so if we don't really
know we shouldn't try to fake our way through it. So that
is one explanation of why משה Moshe said כחצות. kechatzos. Okay, not
because he didn't know. So actually it's interesting, I'll just make a
side comment, my
mother-in-law started with the new cycle with the דף יומי Daf Yomi
to be learning some of it. I'm not sure if she's going
regularly. And she called me the other night when we were actually
like two days ago when she was doing ג' עמוד ב' Gimel
amud beis at the bottom when the first answer was משה Moshe
didn't know before we say here he did know and he you
know and he was doing it because he didn't want them to
think he had made a mistake. So she said, you know, how
is it here the גמרא Gemara says that משה Moshe didn't know?
What are you talking about? Anybody who learns the חומש Chumash and
משה'ס Moshe's כחצות, kechatzos, you've learned that רש"י Rashi over there says
that he's saying it so that the astrologers, you know, he knew
but he didn't want the astrologers to think he made a mistake.
So I said to her I said you know that's the problem
is that the גמרא Gemara. didn't learn רש"י. Rashi. But the reason
I bring up that story is to point out that on the
רש"י Rashi is amazing because other than he's always amazing and רש"י
Rashi on the גמרא Gemara and רש"י Rashi on the תורה, Torah,
but he so much takes a person from the world of learning
חומש Chumash and immerses you into the entire world of תורה שבעל
פה Torah sheba'al peh in a way that it's like completely you
know sort of natural and intertwined, right? And and you know because
it so much interweaves itself with the biblical narrative that you start
and it sometimes that leads to you know not distinguishing between פשט
peshat and דרש, derash, but it also really sort of completely positions
you in the world of תורה שבעל פה. Torah sheba'al peh. But
the thing is then you know then you have to take get
a little distance and really that what even when רש"י Rashi is
doing that he's taking one particular strand. There's often a wide much
wider range of interpretations of what the פסוקים psukim could mean than
the particular one that רש"י Rashi is sort of choosing to bring
in. So it's quite interesting. רש"י Rashi chose this answer of the
גמרא Gemara not the earlier answer of the גמרא. Gemara, Yes.
Water clocks existed in Egypt at
the...
So they
would have been able to get at least very close to it.
Exactly. And then it would have been up to the אצטגניני פרעה,
Itzigninei Paroh, the astrologers. So, you know, maybe the גמרא Gemara didn't
have that historical piece of information. Okay.
So, and also, it's just for information that the psalter from the
Greek,
the psalterion, is a stringed instrument.
It's another stringed instrument. Okay. Another stringed instrument. Okay. So now the
גמרא Gemara continues. רב אשי אמר בפלגא אורחא דתליסר נגי ארבע עשר
הוי קאי. Rav Ashi amar bepalga orchad d'tlsar nagi arba assar havei
kaia. One more answer about why משה Moshe said כחצות, k'chatzot, approximately,
not exactly. Because the כ kaf there does not mean roughly. The
כ kaf means the, it's a comparison כ. kaf. It means משה
Moshe was exactly at midnight of the 13th, the כחצות k'chatzot was
going to be the midnight of the 14th. והכי קאמר ליה משה
לישראל. Vehachi ka'amar leh Moshe l'Yisrael. This is what משה Moshe was
saying to ישראל. Yisrael. אמר הקדוש ברוך הוא, Amar HaKadosh Baruch Hu,
God has told me, למחר כחצות הלילה כי האידנא, lemachar k'chatzot halaylah
ki ha'idna, tomorrow
like midnight right now. So the כ kaf is comparing. It's not
saying, it's not saying approximately כחצות. k'chatzot. It's saying like midnight, like
right now where it's midnight tomorrow at exactly this time אני יוצא
בתוך מצרים. ani yotzei betoch Mitzrayim. So the כ kaf there does
not mean approximately, it means like, like the, like the exact time
we're at right now. Okay, so that's a little bit of a
digression about the כחצות, k'chatzot, all part of this other digression about
the idea of the אשמורה ashmura and דוד David getting up at
midnight. And now we continue with talking about דוד המלך. David HaMelech,
So let's take a look. לדווד, L'David, so here is a מזמור
לדווד, mizmor l'David, for, to דוד. David. שמרה נפשי כי חסיד אני.
Shomrah nafshi ki chasid ani. God, protect my soul because I am
חסיד, chasid, I am a righteous person. לוי ורבי יצחק. Levi v'Rabbi
Yitzchak. So לוי Levi and רבי יצחק Rabbi Yitzchak had a debate
about this. חד אמר כך אמר דוד לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא. Chad
amar kach amar David lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu. This is what דוד
David is saying to God. רבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam, Master
of the Universe, לא חסיד אני, lo chasid ani, am I not
a righteous person? שכל מלכי מזרח ומערב ישנים עד שלש שעות. shekol
malchei mizrach uma'arav yeshenim ad shalosh sha'ot. All the kings of the
East and the West sleep until three hours into the day. I
mentioned yesterday whether that means three full hours till 9:00 a.m. or
the beginning of the third hour, 8:00 a.m., which has significant implications
for how late we say שמע. Shema. Anyway, they all take it
easy. They all sleep until well into the day.
ואני חצות לילה אקום להודות לך. Va'ani chatzot laylah akum l'hodot lach.
I get up at midnight to praise you. So he's taking a
little pride in his accomplishment. Look how much I devote to, to
you and I get up already so much earlier. ואידך, V'idach, the
other one, interpreted it in a different way. כך אמר דוד לפני
הקדוש ברוך הוא. Kach amar David lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu. This is
how דוד David says to God. רבונו של עולם, Ribono Shel Olam,
Master of the Universe, לא חסיד אני, lo chasid ani, am I
not righteous? שכל מלכי מזרח ומערב יושבים אגודות אגודות בכבודם. shekol malchei
mizrach uma'arav yoshevim agudot agudot bichvodam. All the other kings, what do
they do when they're, not how early they wake up, but what
do they do when they're actually active during the day? They're sitting
with all of their retinues, all of the people there to, you
know, the guards and the, and the hangers-on and their entire retinues
בכבודם, bichvodam, in their honor and glory, and they're very much sort
of the, you know, the position that they're, that they're embodying is
one of bringing glory to themselves and honor to themselves. ואני, Va'ani,
what do I do when I get up and I go start
my working day? ידי מלוכלכות בדם ובשפיר ובשליא. yadai meluchlachot b'dam uv'shapir
uv'shilya. My hands get dirty with the blood and with the, with
the embryo and with the placenta, כדי לטהר אשה לבעלה, k'dei letaher
isha l'va'alah, in order to say that a woman can be pure
to her husband. So רש״י, and we just started with ברכות Berachot
and not just finished learning נידה. Niddah. רש״י tells us a lot
of things we just learned a little while ago in נידה. Niddah.
That although a woman who sees blood, not all colors of blood
make her a נידה, Niddah, so you have to look and inspect
the blood. If a woman has a miscarriage, sometimes the way the
fetus is or the way the placenta is, she's not considered to
be a יולדת, yoledet, so she also, in some cases, would not
be טמאה. tmeiah. So דוד David says, look what I do. I
dirty my hands in this, I bloody my hands in this, in
order because my role is also to, you know, I care so
much for each individual and I'm involved in the, you know, the,
the daily little details of הלכה. halacha. Now, what I find fascinating,
well, a couple things I find fascinating, I, like, I don't really
know the answer, I'd be curious to hear your, your take about
this, is this is a very, I think, graphic image. And anybody
who's learned this גמרא, Gemara, I mean, I learned it, you know,
decades ago, you know, I think that really sticks with you. Like,
here's דוד David המלך, right? He's on, he's not on his throne,
he's not surrounded by his retinue, there he is getting his hands,
like, looking at the placenta and the embryo and the blood. So
in the sense of, like, look how much I'm different from the
kings. It's very graphic. But it does, you know, it's interesting, I
think, that the rabbis, and we'll see it as it continues, want
to imagine דוד David not just as like, you know, the one
who writes תהילים Tehillim and sings God's praises and not just the
king of ישראל, Yisrael, and not just the one who follows God,
but wants to imagine him as like, you know, a rabbi, as
a תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, as somebody who learns הלכה, halacha, פוסק
הלכה. pasken halacha. People come to him with הלכה halacha questions, and
other people to ask these questions to, you know, maybe you come
to the king, like, if there's a debate and it keeps on
getting pushed up and finally you get an audience with the king.
Like, you don't imagine that an individual person who has a personal
הלכה halacha question, even if the king deals
why they're so invested in David playing that role and particularly the
degree to which they seem playing it at this very sort of
personal level. Did you want to say something about that?
Just thought of it, it's a reminiscence of the blood on his
hands.
Oh, you mean because your hands are—that's fascinating. That's a very beautiful
idea. That why he—why it says you're not going to build the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash because your hands are filled with blood. Right,
very nice. I hadn't thought about that. Yes. You want to say
something? No?
Okay, so טוב, tov, any thoughts?
Well, you—also, he had blood on his hands a minute ago by
telling them to go to war.
Well, guys, that's picking up on what David said. Right.
So he also with בת שבע, Bas Sheva, another place. Right.
So right, right, right. Taking the idea of David of the bloody
past and reframing it. Yeah, that's a very nice idea.
Or with women specifically, he's playing a role
as—okay, as opposed to taking—taking, right, to get away, to get—to kill
the husband to get her away from her husband, bring the husband
together with the husband, right?
And causing a miscarriage also.
Right, right. Causing a stillbirth.
Oh, right, right. His child.
Okay, excellent. Great, great. Yes.
So we learn from this גמרא Gemara that it's okay when we
have a request from השם Hashem to mention our own זכויות. zchuyos.
Well, the גמרא Gemara is going to get to that about this
whole idea of praising himself. So let's see where that goes. Okay,
so that's the give and take. Not just that I wake up
early, but look at the role that I play is so profoundly
different from the role that these kings play. Okay, ולא עוד אלא,
v'lo od ela, not only that, אלא כל מה שאני עושה, ela
kol mah she'ani oseh, whatever I do, אני נמלך במפיבושת. ani nimlach
b'Mephibosheth. So before we said that he was going to ask אחיתופל
Achitophel before going to the war. But now he's saying anything I
do, which here specifically means in the halachic area, any halachic ruling
I do, I first ask מפיבושת. Mephibosheth. Where do we get that
from? Because the גמרא, Gemara as we'll see, do a little bit
of a play on words. רבי—and Rebbi here's what I say to
him.
מפיבושת רבי, Mephibosheth Rebbi, מפיבושת Mephibosheth my master, my—my rabbi, ואומר לו
v'omer lo and I say to him: מפיבושת רבי, Mephibosheth Rebbi, יפה
דנתי? yafeh danti? יפה חייבתי? yafeh chayavti? יפה זכיתי? yafeh zachiti?
Did I judge correctly? Did I say correctly that this person is
obligated to pay? That this person is exempt from paying? יפה טיהרתי?
yafeh tiharti? יפה טימאתי? yafeh timati? Was I correct when I said
that this was טהור, tahor, when this was טמא? tamei? So I
ask him all my halachic questions. I know that I'm not—it's again,
I know on the one hand maybe I hold the greatest
halachic authority, but I'm not necessarily the smartest person in הלכה. halacha.
מפיבושת Mephibosheth is—is wiser than I am. So when I rule, but
I ask him whether I've done correctly. ולא בשתי, v'lo boshti, and
I'm not embarrassed. It's interesting, of course, he doesn't ask him before
he rules. He asks him after he rules. So somebody comes to
you with a שאלה, shaylah, you know, turns to the other person
and says what's the answer? You have to actually embody your role
and give the reply, but afterwards you can check up on it.
Okay. And you're the king. And you're the king, right. You don't
defer—somebody comes to the king at that moment. But afterwards, you can
check up and maybe if there was a mistake you can correct
it, and you'll certainly know it for the future. אמר—so—אמר רבי יהושע—so
that's מפיבושת Mephibosheth by the way, that's the point. From his mouth,
right, I get—and בושת bosheth I—and I'm not embarrassed, or I allow
myself to be a little bit like, you know, a little embarrassed,
or I don't—but you know, I do it without hesitation even though
it's an—a potentially embarrassing thing, but I always am—go to him to
see if I've done correctly. Did anybody comment on the—on the similarity
of the name מפיבושת Mephibosheth and ולא בשתי? v'lo boshti? Well, that's
what I just said, that it's a play on words, that it's
saying that that's where the גמרא Gemara is getting the idea that
he asks מפיבושת. Mephibosheth. From his mouth and I did not—yes. But
ולא בשתי v'lo boshti is as if and I wasn't מפיבושת. Mephibosheth.
Right, I did allow myself to be embarrassed by his words. Right.
I—right. Well, I mean take a look at רש"י, Rashi, right? רש"י
Rashi says מפיבושת—about Mephibosheth six lines before it gets wide—רש"י Rashi says
מפיבושת בדברי הלכה היוצא מפי היה בושש אותי. Mephibosheth b'divrei halacha hayotzei
mipi haya boshesh oti. So from the words that would come out
of his mouth, it would be an embarrassment to David שפעמים שהיה
טועה shepe'amim shehaya to'eh because sometimes he would be wrong, ואומר לו
טעית v'omer lo ta'ita and he would say you made a mistake.
So I think the point is it will be embarrassing if you
find out you made a mistake, but I was not embarrassed to
ask. Meaning that רש"י Rashi is sort of balancing it as I
was prepared to ask, I was not
so embarrassed that I did not ask, but if he told me
I did something wrong, that—that would have
been a little embarrassing, but that never stopped me from asking. That's
sort of the way רש"י Rashi is playing that. But yes, it's
clearly the way the גמרא Gemara is getting to that is from
the name.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. אמר רבי יהושע בריה
דרב
אידי,
Amar Rebbi Yehoshua
breih d'Rav Idi, מאי קרא?
Where do you see this? ואדברה בעדותיך נגד מלכים ולא אבוש.
V'adabra b'edosecha neged melachim
v'lo evosh.
I will speak about—this is in the same פרק perek of תהילים
Tehillim of חצות לילה אקום, chatzos lailah akum, right, that he gets
up at midnight, and I will speak about your—about your testimonies, about
your laws in the presence of kings, and I will not be
embarrassed. So again, that's presumably saying two things. Number one, נגד מלכים,
neged melachim, that the kings are going around with all their retinues
and so on, and I'm getting my hands dirty with this blood.
I'm not embarrassed to deal with the daily. aspects of הלכה halacha
because that is an important part of my role and I'm not
embarrassed also to make sure that I'm doing the right thing and
to ask מפיבושת. Mefiboshet. תנא, Tanna, לא מפיבושת שמו אלא איש בושת
שמו. lo Mefiboshet shemo ella Ishboshet shemo. His name wasn't מפיבושת Mefiboshet
but איש בושת. Ishboshet. ולמה נקרא שמו מפיבושת? v'lama nikra shemo Mefiboshet?
Why was he called מפיבושת? Mefiboshet? שהיה מבייש פני דוד בהלכה, shehayah
mevayesh pnei David bahalacha, that he would embarrass דוד David when he
would show up, דוד David would ask him and he would tell
דוד David. sometimes he got it wrong and that would embarrass דוד.
David Not clear if it meant intentionally embarrass, but that would be
the result. לפיכך זכה דוד יצא ממנו כלאב. lefikach zachah David yatza
mimenu Kilav. And because דוד David was willing to expose himself to
this, he merited and he had a son כלאב, Kilav, which is
in one of the places listed as one of the sons of
דוד David in שמואל, Shmuel. that's the wife of, the son of
אביגיל. Avigail. So why exactly כלאב? Kilav? ואמר רבי יוחנן, v'amar Rabi
Yochanan, לא כלאב שמו אלא דניאל שמו. lo Kilav shemo ella Daniel
shemo. In another place, in דברי הימים, where it mentions the list
of the sons, instead of כלאב Kilav it says דניאל. Daniel. So
the גמרא Gemara in many places tries to deal with those contradictions
by really saying, reconciling them, they're all the same. So if his
real name was דניאל, Daniel, why was he called כלאב? Kilav? ולמה
נקרא שמו כלאב? v'lama nikra shemo Kilav? שהיה מכלים פני מפיבושת בהלכה,
shehayah machlim pnei Mefiboshet bahalacha, because כלאב Kilav showed up מפיבושת. Mefiboshet.
So כלאב Kilav is like מכלים, machlim, to embarrass, and אב, av,
מפיבושת Mefiboshet who had been the father, meaning the master, of הלכה.
halacha. So דוד David. in the end because he allowed himself to
be embarrassed because he wanted to make sure he was doing the
right thing, he was זוכה, zocheh, he would merit that his son
would be even greater than מפיבושת. Mefiboshet. Yeah, let me just finish.
ועליו אמר שלמה בחכמתו, v'alav amar Shlomo b'chochmato, בני אם חכם לבך
ישמח לבי גם אני, beni im chacham libcha yismach libi gam ani,
my son, if your heart is wise, my heart will also be
joyous, which on the one hand just really means that parents are
very happy when their children are successful, even more successful than they
are. But here it's saying that he's very happy because he was
so successful he showed up מפיבושת. Mefiboshet. ואומר, v'omer, and it says,
חכם בני ושמח לבי ואשיבה חורפי דבר, chacham beni v'samach libi v'ashivah
chorfi davar, my son has been wise, my heart has rejoiced, I
will respond to those that sort of shame me, but also like
degrade me, I have a word to respond to them. So by
the way, I should say that the way it's being framed here,
it doesn't just sound like it was incidental that מפיבושת Mefiboshet embarrassed
דוד. David There seems to be something like מפיבושת Mefiboshet didn't exactly
go out of his way to reduce the embarrassment and that therefore,
because there's a sense of like comeuppance here, not just that דוד
David is glad he has a bigger תלמיד חכם talmid chacham son,
but that מפיבושת Mefiboshet is the חורפי, chorfi, is like the one
that cursed me out and now my son is showing him up.
So it suggests a very interesting dynamic that מפיבושת Mefiboshet would actually,
would really be an embarrassing experience for דוד David because of the
way מפיבושת Mefiboshet treated it and then in the end sort of
this was, there was some comeuppance there. Yeah, he also does a
דרשה, derasha, right? What? אביגיל, Avigail, yeah, שמואל. But didn't it say
she was not, מיכל Michal was, מיכל Michal was sort of a
רשעת, rasha'at, yeah. It says here be wise my son and glad
my heart, I will respond to what disgraces me. Disgraces is really
humiliating. Right. And that's very different from being going to someone as
a source to correct you or to give you a wiser... right,
and the person treats you... right. And yeah, you can give response
and correction and constructive criticism in a very respectful way. Right, that's
exactly my point. In a constructive way also, right, and constructive, right.
The fact that it's being framed as חורפי, chorfi, right, so that's
an interesting translation, disgrace, I would say חורפי chorfi is also like
to curse somebody out, and yeah, it's all of that sort of
constellation of ideas. So right, that sort of understands that מפיבושת Mefiboshet
was acting in a very particular way and then it's fascinating that
דוד David, was still willing to subject himself to that. Okay. So
now we continue. דוד, David now it gets to the question that
was asked before. ודוד מי קרי לנפשיה חסיד? v'David mi kari l'nafsheih
chasid? דוד David called himself a חסיד? chasid? והכתיב, v'haktiv, the פסוק
Pasuk says, לולא האמנתי לראות בטוב ה' בארץ חיים, lulei he'emanti lir'ot
b'tuv Hashem b'eretz chayim, had I not had that I would have
given despair had I not had the faith that I would see
ultimately in the good of God in the land of the living.
So when I was being chased and by my enemies, I would
have despaired had I not had faith that ultimately God would, I
would see, I would see the good life and God would protect
me, which is understood by the גמרא Gemara means עולם הבא, Olam
Haba, that's the sense of ארץ חיים. eretz chayim. ותנא משמיה דרבי
יוסי, v'tana mishmeih d'Rabi Yosi, we taught in the name of רבי
יוסי, Rabi Yosi, למה נקוד על לולא? lamah nakud al lulei? Why
is there a dot over the word לולא? lulei? אמר דוד לפני
הקדוש ברוך הוא, amar David lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, to show that
he didn't necessarily, like he says, had I not had faith, but
there's a little dot, which means maybe there were times that I
did not have enough sufficient faith, right, like the יידיש Yiddish expression
וישקהו מיט פינטלעך? vayishakeihu mit pintelach? No? You know it says that
when עשו Esav met יעקב Yaakov it says so he ran over
to him וישקהו vayishakeihu and he kissed him and there are little
dots over the וישקהו. vayishakeihu. So רש"י Rashi says it was all
show, he didn't really feel anything for him. So the יידיש Yiddish
expression is וישקהו מיט פינטלעך, vayishakeihu mit pintelach, he kissed him with
dots. Okay so that's what, so that's what, so that's what's being
said here. No way, like with dots, had I not had faith
with dots. Okay, maybe sometimes actually my faith did falter. So why
did this faith falter? איתמר משמיה דרבי יוסי, Itamar mishmei de'Rabbi Yosi,
למה נקוד על לולא? lama nakud al Lulei? אמר דוד לפני הקדוש
ברוך הוא, Amar David lifnei HaKadosh Baruch Hu, רבונו של עולם, Ribono
Shel Olam, God David says Master of the universe, מובטח אני בך
שאתה משלם שכר טוב לצדיקים לעתיד לבוא. Muvtach ani becha she'ata meshalem
sachar tov latzadikim le'atid lavo. I have no question that You, God,
will reward the righteous in the world to come. So why am
I having, why is my faith faltering? ואיני יודע אם יש לי
חלק ביניהם אם לאו. Ve'eini yodeia im yesh li chelek beineihem im
lav. I don't know if I'm going to merit. Now why not?
Because a minute ago, you know, he knew that he was a
righteous person. שמא, Shema, so here you see דוד David who did
not consider himself righteous and before he said חסיד אני, Chasid ani,
I am pious. So the Gemara answers שמא יגרום החטא. Shema yigrom
hachet. No, he knew that he was righteous when it was important
he could take credit for that, you know, look God, you know,
כי חסיד אני, Ki chasid ani, but that doesn't mean that he
knew that he was in the end in the world to come,
you know, like the other statement לא תאמין בעצמך עד יום מותך,
Lo ta'amin be'atzmecha ad yom motecha, you know, don't trust yourself to
the day of your death. You don't know, you know, just because
you've been good up till now doesn't mean that in the end
it's all going to work out well. Maybe in the end, you
know, I will sin and the sin will cause me to lose
what I've accomplished. So that sense that he was so, which is,
you know, a fascinating also sort of psychological take, that on the
one hand, it's not like you're not aware of who you are,
you know, the whole Jewish concept of modesty and ענווה Anavah and
so on, you're not aware, you know, yes, he knows what he's
accomplished, you know, and even knows in terms of how righteous he
is, okay, but at the same time, you know, there's not this
arrogance, there's always this sense of being aware of frailty and being
aware about the possibility, you know, that you could falter. And at
the same time not, you know, so, so not be overconfident, you
know, being aware of what you've achieved so far but not being
overconfident in terms of, in terms of what that means for the
future. So yeah, if that's the case, what if that's the case
that he really feels at this point since he's a חסיד Chasid
that he did all these past actions? Right, either it's, either it's
a wonderful view of life contextually and saying the things that he
knows he did that were bad don't put him over on the
other side. Right, or he does, or perhaps he does... Well, yes,
that is true. I mean through the Gemara's eyes, the same דוד
David who also is getting his hands dirty with the blood of,
you know, the נידה Niddah and so on, the Gemara does not
get too bothered about some of these, about like, you know, about
some of the things about דוד David. that were not so, you
know, praiseworthy about the whole thing with, you know, with getting אוריה
Uriah killed and all these. I mean there are times where the
Gemara does, you know, focus on that, but very often the Gemara
has a very rosy picture of דוד. David So they're not being
his common and taunting him. Yes, I understand, I understand. But you
know, the Gemara says כל האומר דוד המלך חטא אינו אלא טועה,
Kol ha'omer David HaMelech chata eino ela to'eh, you know, the Gemara
has ways in which really what happened to us was that he
had already given a divorce to his wife before, you know, אוריה,
Uriah, before he sent him to the... and the Gemara reads the
פסוק. Pasuk. Right, but this is also the Gemara reading these פסוקים
Psukim of כי חסיד אני. Ki chasid ani. So it's all within
sort of the Gemara's picture. But okay, but I do think it
is fascinating again that you can take the credit of כי חסיד
אני Ki chasid ani and at the same time, you know, not
that's not arrogant, you know, it's not arrogant because and there's an
awareness that that, you know, every day still, you know, you have
to make the right decision. שמא יגרום החטא. Shema yigrom hachet. רבי
יעקב בר אידי, Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi, רמי רבי יעקב בר אידי,
Rami Rabbi Yaakov bar Idi, showed a contradiction between פסוקים. Psukim. כתיב,
Ketiv, one פסוק Pasuk. says והנה אנכי עמך ושמרתיך בכל אשר תלך.
Vehineh anochi imach ushemarticha bechol asher telech. God promised יעקב Yaakov that
he'd be with him wherever you go. וכתיב, Uketiv, and then it
says when יעקב Yaakov returned ויירא יעקב מאד. Vayira Yaakov me'od. יעקב
Yaakov was very fearful. Why was he fearful? Didn't God promise him?
So אמר, he said yeah, I know God promised me, but שמא
יגרום החטא. Shema yigrom hachet. Maybe sin will cause it to be
lost. Now here it's actually different. Here it's really more in the
past, שמא גרם החטא. Shema garam hachet. Because he was already promised
and his concern was maybe I'm no longer meriting that promise, maybe
my sin has caused me to no longer be deserving. By דוד
it was שמא יגרום Shema yigrom in the future. Is sin יעקב?
Yaakov? The Gemara doesn't say specifically, and I think that that's important.
It's not like it's more of this sort of, you know, from
a righteous person there's a general anxiety about sin, you know, that
obviously could be very bad, right? To always be anxious and whatever.
But sense, that sense that you're, there's always a concern of are
you doing enough, have you done things correctly, will you be doing
things correctly. So I don't think the Gemara, I don't think the
point here is that the Gemara specifies a specific sin that there
was a concern about. I mean we could try to identify it
ourselves, but I don't think that's the point of this Gemara. Is
this just for the construct of Jewish guilt actually starting... I think
there are plenty of sources for that, so. But yes, but this
obviously does reflect that sense that you, but but look, again, it's
also the sense like the Gemara says אשרי אדם מפחד תמיד. Ashrei
adam mefached tamid. Is that the פסוק? Pasuk That says, you know,
that... אשרי אדם? Ashrei adam? What? אשרי אדם מפחד? Ashrei adam mefached?
Thank you. אשרי אדם מפחד תמיד. Ashrei adam mefached tamid. It says
it's praise of the person who's always afraid, גמרא Gemara says that's
the person who's always afraid מן העבירות שבידו min ha'aveiros she'beyado about
you know what he, the sins he might've done, the sins he
will do. So there's this idea that if you really are like
God-fearing and concerned about doing the right thing, you're always agitated, you're
always concerned: have I done enough? Did I do exactly the right
thing? Am I going to be doing the right thing? So that's
like a constant concern. I don't mean that's the same as guilt,
okay? That's more of a, you know, anxiety concern rather than, rather
than feeling guilty about it. Of course, one can lead to the
other. All right, anyway, the גמרא Gemara. continues כדתניא k'detanya עד יעבור
עמך ה' עד יעבור עם זו קנית ad ya'avor amcha Hashem ad
ya'avor am zu kanita by the שיר, Shir, by the ים, Yam,
until your nation passes over, God, this nation that you have acquired.
עד יעבור עמך ה', ad ya'avor amcha Hashem, your nation passes over,
זו ביאה ראשונה, zu biah rishonah, the first coming into the land
of Israel and no longer just crossing over the ים סוף, Yam
Suf, right? We're crossing over into the land of Israel. So this
is the first entering. עד יעבור עם זו קנית, ad ya'avor am
zu kanita, the nation that you acquired, זו ביאה שניה, zu biah
shniyah, that's the second time they came in when they came in
at the time of עזרא. Ezra. מכאן אמרו חכמים mikan amru chachamim
ראויים היו ישראל ליעשות להם נס בימי עזרא כדרך שנעשה להם בימי
יהושע בן נון. reuyim hayu Yisrael le'aseos lahem nes bimei Ezra kederech
shena'asah lahem bimei Yehoshua bin Nun. Because it's being as a parallel
here, going in the first time, going in the second time, the
second time should have been like the first time. They should have
been, you know, independent, sovereign, they should have been able to have
just taken control, you know, conquered the country, as opposed to we
know they went in the second time it was under the permission
of the King of, of the Persian King, and they were very
much a non-sovereign people at the time, even when they built the
בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. So it should have been like the first
time אלא שגרם החטא, ela shegaram hachet, but the sin made it
that yes, they got in the second time, but it wasn't the
same way it was in the first, which is I think a
nice way of ending it because then it says it's not just
a theoretical issue. Like, yeah, yeah, שמא יגרום החטא. shema yigrom hachet.
Actually, sometimes it does happen. There are things that are anticipated and
promised or whatever but it doesn't exactly work out that way because,
because sin gets in the way. There is an interesting question here,
which is a larger issue we're not going to go into, which
is, you know, the question is that רמב"ם Rambam raises, which is,
you know, the רמב"ם Rambam says look, how do you test if
somebody is a נביא? navi? If they promise something and it comes
about. So רמב"ם Rambam says but maybe it doesn't come about, like
you know, יונה Yonah says, you know, what is it? "Yet forty
days and Nineveh shall be overthrown." יונה Yonah says, you know, what
is it, you know, עוד ארבעים יום ונינוה נהפכת, od arba'im yom
v'Nineveh nehepaches, and then it didn't happen because they did תשובה. teshuvah.
So the רמב"ם Rambam says, okay, so if he says something bad
and it doesn't come about, that doesn't prove he's not a נביא
navi because, you know, maybe people did תשובה teshuvah and God had
רחמנות. rachmanus. But if he says something good and it doesn't come
about, that proves he's not a נביא navi because God will never
say anything good and then actually won't come to fruition. So then
the question is, yeah, but what about this, שמא יגרום החטא? shema
yigrom hachet? So of course there could be differences, you know, if
you say it to a נביא navi to be proclaimed officially to
the people it has a different status, you know, than other things.
But here it is an interesting גמרא Gemara that particularly tying it
into these פסוקים pesukim of עד יעבור עמך ה', ad ya'avor amcha
Hashem, you know, and even with יעקב, Yaakov, יעקב Yaakov was given
an
explicit promise, so it's not just a sense of what am I
meriting, but even something God has
promised I might lose if שמא יגרום החטא. shema yigrom hachet.
So it works the other way around too? Does it just a
decree for something good? If there's so, there's a decree for something
bad that שמא יגרום המצוה? shema yigrom hamitzvah? Well yeah, that was
the first point about like about יונה Yonah and נינוה Nineveh and
so on.
That was, that was the first point רמב"ם Rambam made. That okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara goes on: וחכמים אומרים עד חצות. vachachamim
omrim ad chatzos. וחכמים vachachamim come back now finally back to הלכה.
halachah. Okay, וחכמים vachachamim say until midnight. So what are they holding
like? This is a fascinating גמרא. Gemara אי כרבי אליעזר סבירא להו,
ei k'Rabbi Eliezer svira lehu, if they hold like רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer that says a few hours into the day, of the night,
because that's when people are going to sleep, let them say like
רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, so say, you know, four hours into the
night. ואי כרבן גמליאל סבירא להו, v'ei k'Rabban Gamliel svira lehu, if
they hold like רבן גמליאל, Rabban Gamliel, who thinks all night, because
as again, רש"י Rashi says all night of רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel
he says it's not when you're going to sleep but when you're
sleeping, as I suggested the other day, רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel might
more be understanding that the idea of שמע Shema is not so
much going to sleep but it's night שמע Shema and day שמע,
Shema, and if it's night it's the whole night. So if they
hold like that, let them say all night, but midnight doesn't make
any sense, it doesn't fit any model of why שמע Shema should
be limited to midnight. So the גמרא Gemara says: ולעולם כרבן גמליאל
סבירא להו, u'l'olam k'Rabban Gamliel svira lehu, they hold like רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel that in principle it's all night. והא דקאמרי עד חצות,
v'ha d'ka'amrei ad chatzos, why did they say until midnight? כדי להרחיק
אדם מן העבירה, k'dei l'harchik adam min ha'aveirah, to distance you from
sin, כדתניא k'detanya like we taught in the ברייתא, braisa, חכמים עשו
סייג לדבריהם, chachamim asu siyag l'divreihem, the rabbis made a fence around
their words, כדי שלא יהא אדם בא מן השדה בערב, k'dei shelo
yehei adam ba min hasadeh ba'erev, a person shouldn't come home at
night from the field, a long day's work, ויאמר, v'yomar, and he
says, oh I have to daven, so אליך לביתי, eilech l'beisi, let
me first go home, ואוכל קימעא, v'ochal kima, I'll have a little
bit to eat, ואשתה קימעא, v'eshteh kima, a little to drink, ואישן
קימעא, v'ishan kima, I'll first take a little nap, ואחר כך אקרא
קריאת שמע ואתפלל, v'achar kach ekra krias shema v'espalleil, then you know
after let me relax a little, then I'll get around to davening
and saying שמע. Shema. And what will happen? ותחטפנו שינה, v'tachtafenu sheinah,
and sleep will overcome him, ונמצא ישן כל הלילה, v'nimtza yashen kol
halailah, and he'll be asleep the whole night, that so you should
not do that. אלא אבל, ela aval, here's what you gotta do:
אדם בא מן השדה בערב, adam ba min hasadeh ba'erev, you come
back from the field at night, נכנס לבית הכנסת, nichnas l'veis haknesses,
before you even go home you go into the synagogue, because the
synagogue... for exactly this purpose, for example, or maybe right into city
limits. אם רגיל לקרות קורא, im ragil likrot korei, אם רגיל לשנות
שונה, im ragil lishnot shoneh, first you learn a little bit before
davening. Fascinating that it puts this in. Either read a little פסוקים,
psukim, learn a little משנה, mishnah, get yourself in the right mindset,
you gotta transition from a heavy day at work. So maybe what
it's saying is the way you transition is not you take off
your tie and take and have a snack and have a drink,
the way you transition is you do a little learning, get yourself
in the mindset getting ready for davening. וקורא קריאת שמע ומתפלל, v'korei
krias shema umitpallel, then you say your Shema, then you daven, then
you go home. ואוכל פיתו ומברך, v'ochel pito umevarech, then you go
home and you eat your bread, you make a ברכה, bracha, and
that's how you should run your day, or your evening. וכל העובר
על דברי חכמים חייב מיתה. v'chol haover al divrei chachamim chayav misah.
And anybody that transgresses what the rabbis said that goes after midnight,
it's as if they're deserving of death. I have the "as if",
literally, they're deserving of death. So meaning, you gotta really make it
before midnight. We're trying to get you not to sleep through the
whole night, but don't treat the midnight lightly, you gotta make sure
you get it done before midnight. מאי שנא בכל דוכתא דלא קתני
חייב מיתה, mai shna bechol duchtah d'lo kani chayav misah, why in
all other places do we just say this is a rabbinic rule,
we don't say you do it, you're deserving of death? ומאי שנא
הכא דקתני חייב מיתה, umai shna hacha d'katni chayav misah, why here
do we use such harsh language? אי בעית אימא משום דאיכא אונס
שינה, i bayis eima mishum d'ika ones sheina, even because of here
we know that it's so likely for you to slip up, you
know, you'll take a little you'll put your head down and then
you'll sleep away the whole night. So we really have to impress
upon you how important it is to do this right away. ואי
בעית אימא לאפוקי ממאן דאמר תפילת ערבית רשות, v'i bayis eima l'afukei
mimaan d'amar tfilas arvis reshus, קא משמע לן דחובה. ka mashma lan
d'chovah. Coming from a totally different direction, we'll find out later that
there's a debate whether how obligatory is the evening prayer—not evening Shema,
but the evening Shmoneh Esrei, evening prayer. So we wanted to underscore
that it's a real obligation. Because there's a debate, some say it's
not such a real obligation. So we use the phrase חייב מיתה
chayav misah to tell you we're really serious about everything here, not
only about Shema, but about the Shmoneh Esrei, it's all a real
obligation you have to be on top of it. Now I just
want to make two comments about this. One is, I don't really
get how midnight is going to work as me getting me on
top of it. You know, at the time when they don't have
electric lights, nobody's staying up till midnight. So if I say, if
I say to myself, well, I have till midnight, I'm also going
to get first take a break and take a something to eat
and put my head down, so it's not like, oh my god,
you know, I don't see how midnight creates an urgency, is what
I'm saying. You know, that's just question number one. But question number
two, what I don't understand is going on is what does the
גמרא Gemara mean, well, what does he hold like, where does midnight
come up from? Oh, it comes כדי להרחיק אדם מן העבירה. kedei
l'harchik adam min haaveirah. That was the משנה, Mishnah, right? Remember the
משנה? Mishnah? רבן גמליאל's Rabban Gamliel kids came home and he said,
you know, and he said, oh, you have the whole night. And
then the משנה Mishnah went on: ולא זו בלבד אמרו אלא כל
מה שאמרו חכמים עד חצות מצותן עד שיעלה עמוד השחר. v'lo zu
bilvad amru ella kol mah she'amru chachamim ad chatzos mitzvasan ad sheyaaleh
amud hashachar. So what exactly is the גמרא Gemara doing? I mean,
maybe it's just trying to find a way to introduce the ברייתא,
braisa, which is a little bit more descriptive of how you could
come to miss the time, but it's again, it's not really clear
to me the whole question and answer of the גמרא Gemara unless
the גמרא Gemara actually thinks that רבן—you Rabban know, that רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel was the one who said the end of the משנה.
Mishnah. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel said you have the whole night, חצות
chatzos, is just a nice thing, כדי להרחיק אדם מן העבירה. kedei
l'harchik adam min haaveirah. And then they want to say, so what
do the חכמים Chachamim hold? So maybe the point here is that
the real difference is that the חכמים Chachamim are saying חייב מיתה,
chayav misah, that they're saying it's a real cutoff, whereas רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel might sort of be saying, you know, so maybe there's
like a nuance of difference. But again, I really don't understand what
the whole framing question here is since it's pretty explicit in the
משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so that's with the idea of the גמרא Gemara
of עד חצות, ad chatzos, and also the point I also made
about not getting how חצות chatzos creates such a sense of urgency.
Now the גמרא—חייב מיתה is not a halachic statement. No, it's a,
you know, it's a rhetoric statement, a גוזמא gozma rhetoric statement. But
maybe again, you know, maybe it's somehow right. Anyway, I just don't...
meaning the difference is is that how do you read the end
of the משנה Mishnah with this statement about ולא זו בלבד אמרו
אלא כל מה שאמרו חכמים עד חצות מצותן עד שיעלה עמוד השחר?
v'lo zu bilvad amru ella kol mah she'amru chachamim ad chatzos mitzvasan
ad sheyaaleh amud hashachar? Sounds like it's describing the position of the
חכמים Chachamim of עד חצות. ad chatzos. So then what's the גמרא's
Gemara question here? Doesn't really make any sense. So what I'm suggesting,
although it's a stretch, is that maybe the גמרא Gemara understands that
that was רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel talking, and there the עד חצות
ad chatzos was more sort of like, you know, advice. And here
the חכמים Chachamim are saying no, it really becomes the שיעור, shiur,
really becomes the time. Look, there are some... let me maybe spell
it out this way. There are some אחרונים achronim who understand that
according to the חכמים, Chachamim, if you miss חצות, you're not allowed
to say שמע. Shema. That you really have to treat חצות as
the absolute cutoff time, and that's, you know, and they really made
it, although biblically you have the whole night, they really made it
the absolute cutoff time. So that would make it very different than
the, you know, than the sense you get from the end of
the משנה, Mishnah, and that might be the point of the גמרא
Gemara here. Okay, so now let's continue. אמר מר קורא קריאת שמע
ומתפלל. amar mar korei krias shema umitpallel. So you say שמע Shema
and then you daven. That's what we just said about what you're
supposed to do when you at the end of the day. מסייע
ליה לרבי יוחנן. mesayei lei l'Rabbi Yochanan. This supports רבי יוחנן, Rabbi
Yochanan, דאמר רבי יוחנן, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan, איזהו בן עולם הבא, eizehu
ben olam habah, who is a person who merits the world to
come? זה הסומך גאולה לתפילה של ערבית. zeh hasomech geulah litfilah shel
arvis. That first you say שמע, Shema, then you daven, that first
you say שמע. Shema. And then you say שמונה עשרה. Shemonah Esrei.
You juxtapose the גאולה, geulah, גאל ישראל, Ga'al Yisrael, which is the
end of the שמע, Shema, and the שמונה עשרה, Shemonah Esrei, because
we know you do it in the morning, you do it in
the evening as well. So isn't that obvious? No, there's another opinion.
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi אומר omer תפילות באמצע
תקנום. tefillot b'emtza tiknum. The שמונה עשרה's Shemonah Esrei come in the
middle, meaning שמע, Shema, שמונה עשרה Shemonah Esrei in the morning, and
then the evening is שמונה עשרה Shemonah Esrei and then שמע. Shema.
So the שמונה עשרה's Shemonah Esrei are in the middle, the שמע's
Shema are at the end, and you can see why we would
want the שמע's Shema at the end, which the גמרא's Gemara. going
to get to, but it should be clear from the פסוקים. Pesukim.
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. במאי קמיפלגי? B'mai kamiflagi?
What are they debating? איבעית אימא קרא, Iba'it eima kra, איבעית אימא
סברא. iba'it eima svara. Either verses or a logical question. איבעית אימא
סברא, Iba'it eima svara, maybe it's just a logical issue. רבי יוחנן
Rabbi Yochanan סבר savar גאולה מאורתא נמי הויא, geulah me'orta nami haviya,
meaning it's not פסוקים, Pesukim, but it's their own sort of understanding
of things. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan holds that the redemption, right from
when they were redeemed from Egypt, right, this is also I should
mention, part of the question about whether there's a מצוה mitzvah to
say to say יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim at night. You know the
thing we say in the הגדה, Haggadah, לא זכיתי שתאמר יציאת מצרים
בלילות. lo zachiti shete'amer Yetziat Mitzrayim baleilot. I never knew that you
would say יציאת מצרים Yetziat Mitzrayim at night until we learned it
from this פסוק of כל ימי חייך. kol yimei chayecha. Now when
we read that, we think it's talking about saying יציאת מצרים Yetziat
Mitzrayim in the הגדה Haggadah at the night of פסח. Pesach. But
that's really not what it's saying. It's going to be a משנה
בברכות, Mishnah b'Berachot, which is saying how do I know you have
to say the third paragraph of the שמע, Shema, the ציצית, Tzitzis,
which is about God redeeming Israel, which is about the יציאת מצרים?
Yetziat Mitzrayim? Maybe you don't say it at night, because the redemption
happened in the day, it didn't happen at night. So there's a
question, what is the status of, you know, גאולה geulah of the
night from the Exodus from Egypt, and whether there's a מצוה mitzvah
of remembering the Exodus, does it on a daily basis, does it
apply at night as well? How important is the מכת בכורות makat
bechorot which was allowed the Exodus to happen, but wasn't the actual
event of the גאולה geulah itself? So they're saying that this is
the same debate. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says, look, I hold that
there was a real גאולה geulah at night. It was the beginning
of the process. It wasn't the ultimate, but the beginning of the
process. אלא Ella and therefore נמי הויא. nami haviya. אלא גאולה מעלייתא
לא הויא אלא צפרא. Ella geulah me'alyata lo haviya ella tzafra. Right,
the full expression was in the morning, but it really started at
night. And therefore when you say the גאל ישראל Ga'al Yisrael and
the גאולה, geulah, it's really a מצוה mitzvah of זכר יציאת מצרים
zecher Yetziat Mitzrayim and it's a real mention of גאולה. geulah. And
therefore you treat it like we always do, גאולה geulah leads into
שמונה עשרה, Shemonah Esrei, and it's the same thing as the morning.
רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi סבר savar no, כיון
דלא הויא אלא צפרא, keivan d'lo haviya ella tzafra, the real redemption
happened in the morning, לאו גאולה מעלייתא היא, lav geulah me'alyata hi,
what happened at night didn't count so much. So although we say
the third paragraph of שמע, Shema, we say ציצית, Tzitzis, and we
say גאל ישראל, Ga'al Yisrael, it doesn't have the same weight, it's
not really at the time of גאולה, geulah, and therefore you don't
have to juxtapose it with שמונה עשרה. Shemonah Esrei. I'll get back
and discuss the whole idea of juxtaposing in a minute, so let's
read a little more גמרא. Gemara ואיבעית אימא קרא, V'iba'it eima kra,
if you want, they learn it from a פסוק. דשניהם מקרא אחד
דרשו, Dishneihem mikra echad darshu, דכתיב dichtiv בשכבך ובקומך, b'shochbecha uvekumecha, when
you go to sleep and when you rise up. רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan סבר savar מקיש שכיבה לקימה. makish shechivah l'kimah. Going to sleep
is like rising up. מה קימה קריאת שמע ואחר כך תפילה, mah
kimah Kriyat Shema v'achar kach tefillah, which we can all agree, in
the morning first you say שמע Shema and then you daven שמונה
עשרה. Shemonah Esrei. אף שכיבה נמי קריאת שמע ואחר כך תפילה, af
shechivah nami Kriyat Shema v'achar kach tefillah, at night also you say
שמע Shema and then you do שמונה עשרה. Shemonah Esrei. רבי יהושע
בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi סבר savar no, מקיש שכיבה לקימה,
makish shechivah l'kimah, it connects them in a different way. This is
probably a better, more simple read of the פסוק. מה קימה קריאת
שמע סמוך למיטתו, mah kimah Kriyat Shema samuch l'mitato, the same way
in the morning you say קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema right after getting
up, right juxtaposed to being in bed, אף שכיבה נמי קריאת שמע
סמוך למיטתו af shechivah nami Kriyat Shema samuch l'mitato at night also
you say it at the last thing before going to bed. Meaning,
the idea that you say קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema before שמונה עשרה
Shemonah Esrei in the morning and after in the night is a
much nicer fulfillment of the פסוק of בשכבך ובקומך, b'shochbecha uvekumecha, the
first thing you do when you wake up, the last thing you
do before going to bed. Okay, so it doesn't have the same
structure of davening if we think about it as the liturgy. So
the liturgy is קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema and שמונה עשרה Shemonah Esrei
and then this becomes שחרית Shacharit and מעריב. Maariv. It's so very
funny, right? שחרית Shacharit you say שמע Shema and שמונה עשרה Shemonah
Esrei and מעריב Maariv you say שמונה עשרה Shemonah Esrei and שמע.
Shema. So if you're thinking about it, how it gets integrated into
the liturgy, you understand the approach of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. But
if you're thinking about it as the מצוה mitzvah of קריאת שמע,
Kriyat Shema, you understand the approach of רבי יהושע בן לוי, Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Levi, first thing in the morning and last thing at
night. Now I want to say two things. First of all, although
this sounds like a theoretical debate, and of course what we know,
we first say קריאת שמע Kriyat Shema and then we say שמונה
עשרה, Shemonah Esrei, it's not so, it's not so theoretical, because if
you come to שול shul late for מעריב, Maariv, what you actually
do is and the people and everybody is sort of getting ready
to do שמונה עשרה Shemonah Esrei is you do שמונה עשרה Shemonah
Esrei with the ציבור tzibur and then you do קריאת שמע Kriyat
Shema and the ברכות Berachot afterwards. You would not do that by
שחרית. Shacharit. שחרית Shacharit you absolutely must do first שמע Shema and
then שמונה עשרה. Shemonah Esrei. For מעריב, Maariv, if you're it's better
to get תפילה בציבור tefillah b'tzibur and then do קריאת שמע Kriyat
Shema with the ברכות Berachot afterwards. So there is some although we
have a general structure, there is the other possibility there. Now what's
the idea of גאולה סמוך לתפילה? geulah samuch l'tefillah? So there's a
lot of interpretations given. רש"י Rashi basically says that it is when
you when you talk about the גאולה, geulah, you are basically drawing
close to God, right, you're praising God. and grateful about what God
has done to redeem us. So you're moving towards God, God is
moving towards you. And that has to be followed by תפילה, tefillah,
by בקשה bakashah and by the שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh Esrei. And if
it's not followed by it, so it's- Rashi gives the example like
you're knocking on the door and then God opens the door and
then you've already left. Okay, so for רש"י Rashi really, it's not
so much that the שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei needs the גאולה, ge'ulah,
but it's that the גאולה, ge'ulah, you know, needs the שמנה עשרה.
Shemoneh Esrei. It has to sort of once you're doing the גאולה,
ge'ulah, it has to ultimately culminate into the שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei
which is this ultimate the most sort of intimate and intense connection.
You could of course flip it and say that because שמנה עשרה
Shemoneh Esrei is such of this sort of intimate and intense connection,
the way you move into it is through the גאולה. ge'ulah. That's
the way you're able to move into the שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei
is only after experiencing and praising and talking about God having redeemed
us and having that whole form of connection that we have with
God. So those are just some ideas, but there's a lot of
interesting sort of religious thought around the significance of גאולה לתפילה. ge'ulah
litfillah. I'll just say that רב סולובייצ'יק Rav Soloveitchik classically, and these
are maybe ideas we'll talk about as we continue, is very bothered
in general by the idea of שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, about what
allows a human being to stand before God and to make requests.
And it's maybe one thing to say praises, which is what we
do, like in the ברכות berachos of גאולה ge'ulah that precede the
שמע, Shema, but so much central שמנה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei is making
requests. And he understands that you need what's called- he uses halachic
language, a מתיר. mattir. You need something that somehow gives you permission
to be in that- to be standing in that position making those
requests. So for him, the idea of being סומך גאולה לתפילה someich
ge'ulah litfillah is that it's basically it's providing you the מתיר. mattir.
It's saying God, you know, you have redeemed us, you have done
this, you have asked us for this relationship, we have created this
relationship, and that's therefore what allows you to move into. So as
opposed to the way I described it before, which is what religiously
and emotionally prepares you for that, he sees it much more as
sort of what makes it religiously acceptable to be moving into that
mode. Yes. I'm just- I'm very moved by this. In the sense
that we're talking about the שמע Shema when we wake up and
the שמע Shema when we go to bed. It's like a parenthesis
around our lives. And what is it really saying? It's saying the
most important thing we have is love, that the relationship we have
is about our love for השם, Hashem, that we are rededicating our
love and reinforcing and letting השם Hashem know that we love השם.
Hashem. Not only in the morning at the beginning of the day
to the very end. Right. I think that's beautiful and that's correct
and I think that's so much of the שמע Shema is, and
that's part of the פשט pshat of the פסוקים. pesukim. Some would
argue פשט pshat of the פסוקים pesukim is not necessarily a formal
מצוה mitzvah of saying it in the morning and the evening, maybe
it's just talking about all the time. And the way that all
the time is expressed is by the first thing in the morning
the end of the evening and absolutely correct. Okay, so let's read
a little bit more before we get to end. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay. מתיב מר בריה דרבינא. Meisiv Mar Breih
DeRavina. So מר בריה דרבינא Mar Breih DeRavina asked, בערב מברך שתים
לפניה ושתים לאחריה. Be'erev mevareich shtayim lefaneha ushtayim leachareha. So we say
that in the evening you say two ברכות berachos before שמע Shema
and two after שמע. Shema. ואי אמרת. Ve'i amart. Now, ואי אמרת
ve'i amart if you say there's a concept of being סומך גאולה
לתפילה someich ge'ulah litfillah by the evening שמע, Shema, בעי לסמוך. ba'ei
lismoch. So you have to juxtapose them. הא לא קסמיך גאולה לתפילה.
Ha lo kasmeich ge'ulah litfillah. So you're having it- we don't just
say גאל ישראל, Ga'al Yisrael, we say another ברכה berachah השכיבנו Hashkiveinu
עד. ad. So we're not juxtaposing it. Right השכיבנו, Hashkiveinu, right, so
we're not juxtaposing it. So הא בעית למימר השכיבנו, ha ba'is leimeimar
Hashkiveinu, you have to say השכיבנו. Hashkiveinu. אמרי. Amri. To that you
could say no. כיון דתקינו רבנן השכיבנו, Keivan detakinu rabanan Hashkiveinu, since
it's a rabbinic requirement to say it, כגאולה אריכתא דמיא. ke'ge'ulah arichta
damya. It makes it like it's a long mentioning of the גאולה.
ge'ulah. Which is a funny answer because it's a completely different theme.
Meaning the גאל ישראל Ga'al Yisrael is the morning theme, but השכיבנו
Hashkiveinu is the fact that you're davenning מעריב. Maariv. You're not just
saying שמע. Shema. Meaning this is a fascinating part of this whole
מסכת. masechet. Is you take a מצוה mitzvah of שמע, Shema, you
take a שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, and then they become part of
some combined literature. So the השכיבנו Hashkiveinu ברכה berachah is the fact
that you're about to be going to sleep. Okay, but somehow we're
fitting it in and saying yeah, but it still somehow works in
this שמע שמנה עשרה Shema Shemoneh Esrei mode. It's a rabbinic requirement
to- seen as just part of the literature and not really considered
an interruption. So now the גמרא says, דאי לא תימא הכי, de'i
lo teima hachi, if you don't say that, שחרית היכי מצי סמיך?
shacharis heichi matzi sameich? How are you even really juxtaposing in the
morning? Why not? דאמר רבי יוחנן, De'amar Rabbi Yochanan, בתחילה אומר ה׳
שפתי תפתח. betchillah omeir Hashem sefasai tiftach. You start by saying ה׳
שפתי תפתח Hashem sefasai tiftach before you start the שמנה עשרה. Shemoneh
Esrei. ולבסוף אומר יהיו לרצון אמרי פי, Ulevasof omeir yihyu leratzon imrei
phi, let the words of my mouth be for desire. אלא התם,
Ella hasam, כיון דתקינו רבנן למימר ה׳ שפתי תפתח, keivan detakinu rabanan
leimeimar Hashem sefasai tiftach, since the Rabbis say that's how you open
שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, כתפילה אריכתא דמיא. ketfillah arichta damya. It becomes
part of the שמנה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, right? Nobody thinks, oh, שמנה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei starts with ברוך אתה. Baruch Atah. שמנה עשרה Shemoneh
Esrei starts with ה׳ שפתי תפתח. Hashem sefasai tiftach. Once the Rabbis
did it, it becomes part of the literature. So הכא נמי hacha
nami here too, כיון דתקינו רבנן kivan detakinu rabanan למימר lememar השכיבנו,
Hashkiveinu, once they said you do it, כגאולה אריכתא דמיא, kigeulah arichta
damya, it becomes part of the liturgy and therefore becomes like you're
still discussing גאולה. Geulah. Again, what is fascinating about this as I
said is we're taking the core concepts right of גאולה, Geulah, שמונה
עשרה Shemoneh Esrei
and so on, but we're
also trying to create liturgy. And therefore those don't always, certain things
get changed and transformed in the process and the גמרא's saying yes,
but because it is the liturgy, somehow we see that as a
continuation to some degree. That was also the debate before. Do you
say שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei before, after שמע Shema night? From the
perspective of שמע, Shema, you should say שמע Shema then. But from
the perspective of liturgy, you say שמונה עשרה, Shemoneh Esrei, you first
say שמע Shema and then שמונה עשרה Shemoneh Esrei like we do
in the morning. So there are these two themes are gonna constantly
sort of be, you know, in tension as we continue to move
through the מסכת. Masechet. Okay, moving on.